Okay בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today's דף daf is כה, kaf-heh, but
we begin on the top of כד עמוד ב, kaf-dalet amud bet,
and we actually are going to shift gears a bit. We had
an interesting משנה mishnah about, you know, a brother that somebody marries
two women בספק, besafek, and he had two brothers, or two people
did it and each of them have two brothers. Anyway, the end
of that משנה mishnah ended that if they both of the brothers
do יבום, yibum, they shouldn't, one should do חליצה, chalitzah, one should
do יבום, yibum, if they both do יבום, yibum, כנסו, kansu, anyway
the end of the משנה mishnah was, אם
קדמו וכנסו אין מוציאין מידם. im kadmu vekanasu ein motzi'in miyadam. If
they went ahead and they did it and they both of them
did יבום, yibum, then they're allowed to stay married. So this משנה
mishnah now is going to sort of pick up a little bit
on that theme of marriages that are not supposed to happen, but
if they do, you allow them to remain. It's interesting that it
was interrupted with a משנה mishnah which in a way should have
been the very first משנה mishnah of the מסכת, masechet, or at
least the גמרא gemara should have been the first גמרא gemara of
the מסכת masechet that discussed the idea that the older son is
supposed to be the one that the primary obligation of יבום yibum
devolves around, falls on, and that led to the גמרא gemara to
look at the פסוק pasuk about the מצוה mitzvah of יבום, yibum,
what we read last night anyway, about, you know, והיה הבכור אשר
תלד vehayah habechor asher teled and interpret, really get to the פסוקים
pesukim and interpret something about, is it talking that the son is
named after the father, is it talking about that the person who
does the יבום yibum inherits his brother, which is how we interpret.
So it got to some core issues about understanding the פסוקים pesukim
and who has the obligation of יבום yibum and what happens as
a result of יבום. yibum. But that sort of in a way
been a very early discussion that somewhat interrupted things here because now
we get back, as I said, to picking up on the theme
ended by one משנה mishnah back about if a wedding happens that
shouldn't have happened, whether we allow it to remain that way or
not. So with that in mind, let's look at the משנה mishnah
on כד עמוד ב kaf-dalet amud bet and we have the following.
הנחשד על השפחה ונשתחררה, hanichshad al hashifcha venishtachrerah, somebody is suspected about
having an affair with a
slave,
a non-Jewish slave who's owned by a Jew who's quasi-Jewish status, and
somebody suspected having an affair with her and she is now freed
by her master. Could have been his slave also, which of course
happens all the time, cases about, you know, about
sexual abuse or taking advantage of the power imbalance and so on.
Anyway, but even if it was somebody else's slave and she was
freed, או על עובדת כוכבים ונתגיירה, o al ovedet kochavim venityahrah, or
an affair with a non-Jewish woman and then she converted, הרי זה
לא יכנוס. harei zeh lo yichnos. So you should not go ahead
and marry this woman even if presumably there's a rumor, it doesn't
necessarily mean it's true, but don't go ahead and marry this woman.
Why? Because by marrying this woman that there was a rumor that
you were having an affair with, you basically just reinforce the rumor,
'See, it's true, obviously you know, she converted and then got married,
so clearly the rumor was
true.' ואם כנס, veim kanas, and if you did go ahead and
marry her, then אין מוציאין מידו, ein motzi'in miyado, we do not
force them to get divorced. So that's one scenario.
Again, הנחשד על אשת איש, hanichshad al eshet ish, if somebody was
suspected about having an affair with a married woman and then she
was divorced from her husband, actually הוציאוה hotziuha has a language of
they removed her from her husband, so we'll get to that in
the גמרא, gemara, but for now we'll just say she was divorced
from her husband מתחת ידו mitachat yado from her husband, אף על
פי שכנס יוציא, af al pi shekanas yotzi, even if בדיעבד bedie'avad
if he married this woman, he has to go ahead and divorce
her. Why? Because there we are much more concerned that if you
reinforce the rumor that they actually were having an affair, then you
know maybe you start suspecting that the kids she had with her
first husband are ממזרים mamzerim or maybe just in general that's so
much worse because that's a because that's in because that in that
case there is of course in if that were the concern and
we'll talk about that in the גמרא gemara in a little bit
jumping ahead that what you would think about the kids she had
with her first husband, then by making her forcing her to divorce
the second guy, in a way it doubly reinforces the rumor, right?
It's one thing if he marries her. If you go ahead and
force them to divorce after he married her, 'See, they really were
having an affair, that's why the rabbis wouldn't let them stay married.'
So the other problem though here is and the reason we might
be more מחמיר machmir בדיעבד bedie'avad is because in the other cases
it's just an idea of like of spreading a rumor or reinforcing
a rumor. But in this case,
you actually were you know the person in addition to having done
an עבירה, aveirah, the result is that if a woman has an
affair with a man, a married woman has an affair with a
man, she becomes forbidden both to her husband and to the man
that she had an affair with. So then... therefore in the other
two cases where he was, even if it were true that he
was sleeping with this non-Jewish woman or with this slave, he would
not become forbidden to them, there is no הלכה halacha that makes
them forbidden to him. So in those cases it's just the concern
of the rumor, so בדיעבד bedi'avad we let it stand, whereas in
this case there's a concern if the rumor really was true, then
he would not be allowed, you know, biblically to stay to marry
this woman he had an affair with. Of course the remaining question
is but maybe the rumor isn't true? So why should we force
a divorce, maybe it's a false rumor. You know? So we'll take
a look at that in the גמרא. Gemara. But the basic difference
in the second case is, is that it's not just the rumor,
were the rumor to be true, he would not be allowed, you
know, biblically to be married to this woman.
Yes,
Michael, what's your question? Clearly it's just these specific two cases, שפחה
shifcha and נכרית, nochrit, because if there's rumors then we can just
say, alright, well anyone's rumored to be sleeping with anybody, we shouldn't
allow them to get married because oh, they were sleeping around before
they got married.
Well, yeah, but the point is that the, I mean so in
a little way תוספות Tosafot asks the question. I mean, so your
question is what about if it's an issue of פנויה? pnuya? So
if you take a look at תוספות, Tosafot, he says,
where's the תוספות? Tosafot?
If you take, well you know what, we'll read the line in
the גמרא Gemara and then we'll read the תוספות. Tosafot. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this, האי גיורת מהיא? Hai giyoret mahia? It
sounds like fine, don't marry her, but it's a good conversion. A
woman who converted after maybe having had an affair with a Jewish
man and maybe for the purpose of marrying this Jewish man, it
says you shouldn't get married because it'll reinforce the rumor, but it's
but at least it sounds like the marriage, like the conversion is
still binding. So the גמרא Gemara says, רמינהי, remihu, I'll ask you
on this: אחד איש שנתגייר לשום אשה, echad ish shenitgayer l'shum isha,
a man who converted for the sake of getting married to a
woman, ואחד אשה שנתגיירה לשום איש, ve'echad isha shenitgayera l'shum ish, or
a woman who converted for the sake of marrying a man, וכן
מי שנתגייר לשום שלחן מלכים, vechen mi shenitgayer l'shum shulchan melachim, or
somebody who converted to being Jewish for the sake of literally the
table of kings, but basically it means for the sake of the
Jews had it really good. Imagine that, somebody converting to be Jewish
because it was better economically and socially to be Jewish than not
Jewish. Okay, so we'll have to wonder about when that was. לשום
עבדי שלמה, l'shum avdei Shlomo, right, alright. So here's the time, in
the time of עבדי שלמה, avdei Shlomo, wanted to marry one of
the servants of שלמה, Shlomo, although before that time like the servants
of שלמה Shlomo weren't Jewish. Anyway, אינם גרים, דברי ר' נחמיה. einam
gerim, divrei Rabi Nechemia. ר' נחמיה Rabi Nechemia says בדיעבד, bedi'avad, if
you do it for ulterior motive, it's not a good, you're not
a good convert. שהיה ר' נחמיה אומר, shehaya Rabi Nechemia omer, because
ר' נחמיה Rabi Nechemia used to say, אחד גירי אריות, echad gerei
arayot, whether if somebody converted because the lions scared them into it,
ובאחד ve'echad sort of evoking the whole story about the Samaritans in
the, in תנ"ך Tanakh at the end of בית ראשון, Bayit Rishon,
ואחד גירי חלומות, ve'echad gerei chalomot, or because of a dream, maybe
because you had a dream that scared you or the way רש"י
Rashi says it is is that people that have visions told you
that you had to, that you had to convert. So you were
doing it again because you were afraid of some consequences of not
converting, but not because of real religious motivation. ואחד גירי מרדכי ואסתר,
ve'echad gerei Mordechai ve'Esther, or ורבים מעמי הארץ מתיהדים כי נפל פחד
היהודים עליהם. verabbim me'ammei ha'aretz mityahadim ki nafal pachad haYehudim aleihem. That's
a perfect example of converting because you're afraid and for ulterior motive.
You could have also mentioned those that converted in the time of
the חשמונאים, Chashmonaim, once we're dealing with historical reasons why people converted
not because of proper religious motive. So anyway, all those interestingly are
out of fear. Anyway, אינם גרים, einam gerim, none of them are
true גרים, gerim, עד שיתגיירו בזמן הזה, ad sheyitgayeru bazman hazeh, until
they convert nowadays. מאי "בזמן הזה" סלקא דעתך? Mai 'bazman hazeh' salka
daitach? What's so important about converting nowadays? אלא אימא "כביזמן הזה", ela
eima 'kivzman hazeh', like things are nowadays, where the Jews don't have
it too good and don't have it too bad. So they're not
converting because they think it'll be better to be Jewish or they're
not converting because they're afraid of some consequences. They're converting out of
true religious motivation. So that's what ר' נחמיה Rabi Nechemia says. Our
משנה Mishnah suggests not that way, that she's a full convert, the
only question is getting married. So the גמרא Gemara says, הא איתמר
עלה, ha itmar alah, so how could that be? Because right now
we only have the voice of ר' נחמיה. Rabi Nechemia. So the
גמרא Gemara says, it was said about it, הא איתמר עלה, אמר
רב יצחק בר שמואל בר מרתא משמיה דרב: הלכה כדברי האומר כולם
גרים הם. ha itmar alah, amar Rav Yitzchak bar Shmuel bar Marta
mishmei deRav: halacha k'divrei ha'omer kulam gerim hem. No, we don't rule
like ר' נחמיה, Rabi Nechemia, we rule like the one who says
they're all גרים, gerim, which is quite fascinating, right? We haven't even
quoted a different תנא. tanna. We've just sort of asserted the presence
of a different voice, כולם גרים, kulam gerim, and we've פסקנ'ד paskened
that way. Okay, which is already quite fascinating.
Now, רב Rav can be a תנא.
tanna. כולם גרים, kulam gerim, yeah, okay, כולם גרים. kulam gerim. But
it says "כדברי האומר כולם גרים הם". k'divrei ha'omer kulam gerim hem.
So the גמרא Gemara now says, I'll get back to this in
a minute, but בדיעבד bedi'avad yes, she is a good גיורת. giyoret.
So the גמרא Gemara says, אי הכי לכתחילה נמי? i hachi l'chatchila
nami? So then why shouldn't she get married to this woman who
converts? So the גמרא Gemara apparently initially thought that maybe the conversion
was suspect. And maybe the reason not to get married, if a
woman converted after there was a rumor that she was having an
affair with a Jewish man, was because maybe it wasn't a full
conversion, and that's why not to get married. But now that you're
saying it's a full conversion, why not get married? Of course that
logic wouldn't have worked in the case of a שפחה, shifcha, because
if you free a שפחה, shifcha, you free a שפחה. shifcha. There's
no quasi, you know, it's not like their motivation... is completely irrelevant.
It's the reality of once she's free she becomes Jewish. So the
גמרא Gemara says if she's fully Jewish now that she converted and
the slave is fully free and therefore a fully Jewish woman, why
should this man not marry her? So the גמרא Gemara says, לכתחילה
נמי, lekhatchila nami, so משום דרב אשי, mishum de-Rav Ashi, because of
what רב אשי Rav Ashi says, דאמר רב אשי, de-amar Rav Ashi,
הסר ממך עקשות פה, haser mimecha ikshus peh, remove from yourself the
perversion of the mouth, ולזות שפתים, velizus sefasayim, and the sort of
the rumor of the lips, meaning try don't, you know, avoid having
a, you know, a bad rumors and bad things being said about
you. So therefore you should not reinforce all these rumors and therefore
don't marry this woman that you were having that you were a
suspect of having an affair with. Okay, the question of course always
is that well, if he really was having an affair then he
probably really would want to marry her and how much is he
going to be bothered, you know, by reinforcing the rumor? But חז"ל
Chazal are really saying that it's not just your own personal concern
about what people say, you know, there's also a societal importance of
not sort of becoming acceptable, you know, oh people go ahead and
have affairs and then they get married or whatever. So it raises
interesting questions that try to control a certain type of a discourse
within the society, whatever the actual facts might be, if things get
sort of, you know, reinforced, these behaviors and talked about and so
on, it just encourages, you know, more behavior along those ways. But
בדיעבד bediavad actually they are allowed to stay married. Now I want
to deal with two points quickly and then take questions. תוספות Tosafot
first of all asks Michael's question. משום דרב אשי והסר ממך עקשות
פה. Mishum de-Rav Ashi ve-haser mimecha ikshus peh. אמרי דבניתן על הפנויה
אין להחמיר לכנוס משום לזות שפתים. Omrei de-benitan al ha-penuya ein le-hachmir
likhnos mishum lizus sefasayim.
How about somebody's rumored to just, you know, two single people to
be sleeping together? Maybe they shouldn't get married because it reinforces the
rumor. He says, no, דאדרבה מצוה לכונסה דבאנוסה כתיב ולו תהיה לאשה.
de-adaraba mitzvah le-khonasa de-ba-anusa kesiv ve-lo sihye le-isha.
Yeah, it's funny he quotes אנוסה anusa again and not מפתה, mefuta,
but he says, no, what you're supposed to do in that case
is to go ahead and, so nobody approves of the bad behavior,
but then the proper thing is to get married, whereas if somebody
is having an affair with a non-Jewish woman or with a slave
or whatever, the proper thing is to break it off. You know,
whereas here the proper thing is to get married. So therefore getting
married as a result actually, of course, you know, the question's still
open. Okay, but it still reinforces the rumor that it actually happened.
All right, it's an interesting question. But the behavior we'd like to
see in that case is them to get married. So that's the,
that's that issue. Now the issue by גירות geirus I need to
say that this is an extremely central גמרא Gemara relating to issues
about גירות geirus because the question is there are two questions about
גירות. geirus. One, well there's a lot of questions, but the two
big questions nowadays are number one, what constitutes sufficient sense of, you
know, commitment, קבלת מצוות? kabbalas mitzvos? How, what is the definition of
that requirement? And the other is the question about motivation because and
often those are intertwined. If someone's only converting for the sake of
marriage, how much are they really committed to become Jewish and so
on? This גמרא Gemara does not at all deal with the depths
of commitment. You could say that the concern about converting for a
wrong purpose that רבי נחמיה Reb Nechemya expresses is because if you're
converting for a wrong purpose you won't really be committed to observe.
But there's no hint of that in what רבי נחמיה Reb Nechemya
says. And it sounds like what רבי נחמיה Reb Nechemya is saying
is is that ulterior motives is itself invalidates the process. For it
to be a legitimate process it has to be motivated religiously. We
rule against רבי נחמיה. Reb Nechemya. We rule that בדיעבד bediavad not,
that it can be having these other at least בדיעבד bediavad it
can have these other motivations.
Then it becomes a big question because while that's בדיעבד, bediavad, לכתחילה
lekhatchila you're not supposed to convert for the sake of marriage and,
you know, that's like what all the halakhic literature said. Of course,
you know, now conversions for the sake of marriage happen all the
time, all the time, you know, and even
in, you know, and sort of
like within the range of Orthodox conversions, especially if people already intermarried
and then they want to be converted and so on. So there's
a lot of interesting תשובות teshuvos about how these concerns about conversion
for the sake of marriage are less serious concerns nowadays even at
the לכתחילה lekhatchila level. One primary תשובה teshuva written by
what's his name?
Nu...
I can't think of the name.
The name is escaping me.
Anyway, an early פוסק posek in anyway
about a hundred years ago... no, no, no,
not in Israel. Here in the... no,
in Europe and then here... all right,
I'll think of the name. Anyway, the תשובה teshuva basically said that
look, in the past when you weren't allowed to or, you know,
society, forget legally whatever, you wouldn't be able to marry, a non-Jew
couldn't marry a Jew unless one of them had converted. So then
the whole conversion was totally in order to enable the marriage. It
says whereas nowadays, you know, people often, you know, people can totally
marry across religions. There's nothing stopping people from marrying across religions. So
to convert is not to make it possible. possible to get married.
Often to convert has to do with other reasons like because your
future spouse wants you to be Jewish, so it's not and or,
you know, there's some something else there that's just about removing, you
know,
the obstacle to getting married. And sometimes, you know, you would have
gotten married anyway, but, you know, the family of your spouse says
no, I can only be married to a Jew or this or
that. Well, so only married then it is an obstacle from the
spouse's perspective. That's true. But the basic argument, but the argument being
that often therefore the motivation has a little bit more to do
with the desire to identify Jewish and not just to remove an
obstacle. Because there aren't really obstacles nowadays and often you have cases
where people are like already married, an intermarriage, they're already married. So
they're already married and then they want to go ahead and convert.
It's not in order to become married, it's in order to be
more Jewish.
So, anyway, there's a lot of interesting תשובות teshuvot around that and
in general around like we live in a very בדיעבד bediavad reality
right now anyway. So it's all very nice to say לכתחילה lechatchila
but basically you say okay, I'm not going to convert you, לכתחילה
lechatchila not allowed to convert. Then they'll say fine, then they go
ahead and get married without converting, right? And then is that the
better, like okay so we're already dealing in a בדיעבד bediavad reality,
right? The בדיעבד bediavad reality is either they're going to get married
without the spouse converting or they're going to get converted for ulterior
motives. Which is the better בדיעבד? bediavad? So these are the types
of, like, you know, חשבונות cheshbonot and a lot of this has
radically changed nowadays in practice about you know so much of the
conversions that happen are related to marriage issues. I will say that
another interesting related question becomes, and this is so fascinating, that some
people raise, no, no, it's not just a לכתחילה lechatchila problem because
when you convert you have to accept all מצוות mitzvot and you
can't and even if you say, not here, that's it'll be a
סוגיא sugya later, okay. Here's just about motivation. You have to accept
all מצוות mitzvot and look some of this is debated what exactly
the parameters of this is but here's an argument. And even if
you don't exclude one rabbinic מצוה mitzvah it's not good, it's not
considered קבלת מצוות. kabbalas mitzvos. So here if somebody basically converts and
when they're not supposed to get and they're planning on getting married
then they're not accepting all the מצוות mitzvot because they're planning on
violating the הלכה halacha of not getting married after you convert and
having been having an affair with, with you know with a Jewish
person. So that should make it a not good בדיעבד bediavad conversion
because you're planning on violating this הלכה. halacha. Okay, that's a pretty
extreme position. But basically this גמרא gemara is a very central issue
around the question about the need for motivation, sincere motivation, which totally
we פוסקין pasken that's a לכתחילה lechatchila not a בדיעבד bediavad against
רב נחמיה. Rav Nechemya. Yes, Charlie.
Might that פוסק posek be the thing Rabbi David Zvi Hoffmann?
No. He has a lot of—there's a lot of these but an
important initial תשובה, teshuvah, I can't believe why I can't remember who
it is, what? נודע ביהודה?
Nodah
BiYehudah?
No, no, no, it was after that. Everybody's going to guess famous
פוסקים. poskim.
Why can't I think—Yeah, I don't know why I can't remember the
name but it'll come to me. Yes.
You keep on saying affair, this עובדת כוכבים ovedet kochavim or the
שפחה shifcha were not זנויות, znuyot, they were—No,
I don't mean by affair that it was adultery, I just mean
they were having a sexual relationship. Okay. Alright. So now the גמרא
gemara says like this. Okay. So the
גמרא gemara says okay. תנו רבנן, Tano Rabbanan, אין מקבלים גרים לימות
המשיח. ein mekabelim gerim limot haMoshiach. We won't accept גרים gerim in
the time of משיח Moshiach because sure that's when everybody will want
to convert, you know, no, you know, so no, you needed to
have converted when it was a little bit harder. Yes.
כיוצא בו, Kiyotzei bo, well, okay, right.
כיוצא בו, Kiyotzei bo, I mean that'll be at people's discretion. לא
קיבלו גרים לא בימי דוד ולא בימי שלמה. lo kibelim gerim lo
bimei Dovid velo bimei Shlomo. So here's about the question about when
it was, you know, don't accept גרים gerim because if they're doing
it for ulterior motives because they want to have it good. אמר
רבי אלעזר Amar Rabbi Elazar מאי קרא? mai kra? What's the פסוק?
pasuk? הן גור יגור אפס מאותי מי גר אתך עליך יפול. Hein
gor yagur efes me'oti mi gar itach alayich yipol. So הן גור
יגור Hein gor yagur
is means to dwell but here it's being read if somebody if
a גר ger comes to convert, גר יגור, ger yagur, גר ger
comes to convert, אפס מאותי efes me'oti it has to be without
me, it has to be like without all of the, you know,
of the benefit, without all the obvious reward. And then מי גר
אתך mi gar itach somebody who converts with you when things are
not good עליך יפול alayich yipol then we'll have a portion with
you in the future. Okay. It raises questions, you know, תוספות Tosafot
raises, again this gets to the issue of the בדיעבד, bediavad, so
תוספות, Tosafot, so לא בימי דוד ולא בימי שלמה, lo bimei Dovid
velo bimei Shlomo, תוספות Tosafot says מאתי הגתי ובת פרעה דבימי שלמה
לא קשיא. me'itay haGitti uvat Paroh debimei Shlomo lo kashya.
How about we do know that people converted, you know, in time
of שלמה, Shlomo, all the people שלמה Shlomo married, etc. דמדי הודהימו
אלא משום שולחן מלכים, Demidihudaimu ela mishum shulchan melachim, ואנו לא
צריכי. vanu lo tzerichi. Alright. Because they anyway were rich, so it
wasn't really ulterior motives. אבל קשה דמצינו בערכין Aval kasheh demnin ba'arug
גבי מעשה דגבעונים בימי דוד נתאספו גרים על ישראל ק"נ אלף, gabei
ma'aseh deGivonim bimei Dovid nit'asfu gerim al Yisrael k'n elef, right, so
whatever 150,000 גרים, gerim, ויש לומר דמצמן נתגיירו. veyesh lomar dem'atzman nitgayeru.
כדאשכחן k'dashkachan במרדכי be'Mordechai ואסתר v'Esther ורבים v'rabbim מעמי me'ammei הארץ ha'aretz
מתייהדים. mityahadim. ויש אומרים v'yesh omrim דלא de'lo קיבלו kiblu גרים gerim
לא lo בימי bimei דוד David ולא lo בימי bimei שלמה Shlomo
אלא ela שנעשו she'nasu גרים gerim גרורים. grurim. So
what does this exactly mean מיעצמן? me'atzman? The Rambam says that it
was like a בית דין של הדיוטות Beit Din shel Hedyotot who
were מקבל mekabbel them. Meaning they weren't supposed to convert, but any
בית דין Beit Din can convert somebody, and בדיעבד bedi'avad it works.
So the reality is, yes, לכתחילה lechatchila you're not supposed to, but
as I was sort of talking about contemporary reality, it happens all
the time and we sort of said that now we're anyway living
in the בדיעבד bedi'avad reality, so it's one בדיעבד bedi'avad over another.
But historically, there have been a lot of cases where בדיעבד bedi'avad
this is exactly what happened and then בדיעבד bedi'avad it actually works,
as we said. You had, what was the story with Mordechai and
Esther or the story about the חשמונאים? Chashmonaim? David, you had a
question? Yeah.
Even the Mordechai and Esther.
Yes, so that's what we said. So, you know, בדיעבד bedi'avad it
might have worked. Okay, very quickly, Josh.
I'm going to ask about בת פרעה. Bat Paroh.
Well, that's what Tosafot asked. Yeah, right.
And I'm going to ask about the ערב רב. Erev Rav. What
do you say about that? I mean, it says Moses not a
בית
דין של הדיוטות.
Beit
Din shel Hedyotot.
All right, I don't know if they ever converted. There was always
people that were hangers-on. Okay, let's move on. With שלמה קלוגר, Shlomo
Kluger, and the name would come to me, so רבי שלמה קלוגר,
Rabbi Shlomo Kluger, he wrote one in an early תשובה teshuva about
how now in America, now whatever, now it's the reality that people
get married even without converting. The idea that you can't convert if
people are anyway living together and planning on getting married is a
very different type of a חשבון. cheshbon. Okay. הנחשד על אשת איש.
hanichshad al eshet ish. Somebody who's now suspected of having an affair
with a married woman, they even בדיעבד bedi'avad have to get divorced
because if it's true, then they're not allowed even דאורייתא de'Oraita to
be married. The question is, how do you know it's true? Maybe
it's not true. So let's take a look. This becomes a very
important discussion about what type of evidence you need for adultery to
create this problem. So אמר רב, Amar Rav, Rav says, ובעדים. ube'edim.
The only time that you would force a divorce if they got
married after there was this rumor of an affair of adultery would
be if there were witnesses that they actually, actually adultery was committed.
And then you know objectively that she's אסור assur to the guy
she had the affair with, and then you force them to get
divorced. But if it's a סתם stam of rumor,
then... Would he be killed? There were עדים edim with התראה, hatra'ah,
whatever. So okay, we're not dealing that there's a בית דין Beit
Din that does דיני נפשות, dinei nefashot, but there's witnesses enough that
she did it, that therefore and only then do you force her
to get divorced. Otherwise, it's a rumor, and we're not going to
force her to get divorced if she marries the other guy. So
the גמרא Gemara says אמר רב ששת, Amar Rav Sheshet, so said
Rav Sheshet,
אמינא, amina, I said, כי ניים ושכיב רב אמרה להאי שמעתתא. ki
nayim v'shachiv Rav amrah l'hai shemateta. Rav must have been falling asleep
when he said that. Why? דתניא, detanya, we taught a ברייתא, Baraita,
הנחשד על אשת איש והוציאוה על ידו, hanichshad al eshet ish v'hotzi'uha
al yado, somebody who's suspected of having an affair with a married
woman and she was divorced as a result, ונתגרשה, v'nitgarsha,
and then she was divorced from her first husband, and then ונתגרשה
מתחת ידו v'nitgarsha mitachat yado על ידי אחר, al yedei acher, and
then she married somebody else. So she was suspected of having an
affair with Reuven, then she went ahead and she married Shimon,
okay, not his brother, okay, she married Barak, okay, so she married
a different guy, not the guy she was suspected of having an
affair with. And then she got divorced from guy number two. Then
אם כנס לא יוציא, im kanas lo yotzi, then if Reuven marries
her after that, he can stay married to her. Now you understand
why, because the fact that she went and married after her divorce
a completely different guy, you know, will undermine any rumors that she
was having an affair with Reuven. If she was having an affair
with Reuven, she would have married Reuven. So clearly, if she went
ahead and married some other person, presumably she wasn't having an affair
with Reuven. Okay, and by the time she gets around to getting
divorced from guy number two and marrying Reuven, people have either forgotten
about it or it's anyway been thrown into enough doubt because of
the fact that that was not the first man that she married.
So in that case she's allowed to, she shouldn't לכתחילה lechatchila marry
Reuven even in that case, but אם כנס לא יוציא, im kanas
lo yotzi, if she married Reuven in that case, she doesn't have
to get divorced. So היכי דמי, heichi dami, what's the case? אי
דאיכא עדים, ei d'ika edim, if it's the case that there were
witnesses that she had an affair with Reuven, so כי אתא אחר
ואפסקה לקלא, ki ata acher v'afskah l'kala, just because somebody came and
interrupted the rumor, מאי הוה, mai hava, why should that make a
difference? We know as a fact she had an affair with Reuven,
we should always force a divorce. אלא לאו דליכא עדים, ela lav
delika edim, it must be that there are no witnesses and therefore
it matters, did she marry Reuven right away or only after another
guy?
וטעמא דאתא אחר ואפסקה לקלא, v'ta'ama d'ata acher v'afskah l'kala, and the
reason therefore that she can stay married to Reuven is because there
was this other guy in the middle who interrupted the rumor. הא
לאו הכי, ha lav hachi, if there was not that scenario, מפקינן,
mafkinan, we would make her get divorced from Reuven, which seems like
a very good proof. It's impossible to understand the scenario with witnesses,
then we would never let her stay married to Reuven. It must
be without witnesses. And it's telling you, if the rumor was interrupted,
she can stay married to Reuven. If the rumor wasn't interrupted, she
can't stay married to Reuven, even though there were no witnesses to
the fact of an affair. So you see a rumor of an
affair will force a divorce if she marries the other guy.
but will force a divorce from the other guy. So the גמרא
Gemara says, we'll see about her husband in a minute. So הלא
הכי מפקינן? Hala hachi mafkinan? So obviously, isn't that a proof against
רב Rav that you would force a divorce from ראובן Reuven even
without witnesses? So אמר לך רב, Amar lach Rav, רב Rav will
say to you, הוא הדין דאף על גב דלא אתא אחר ואפסקה
לקלא. Hu hadin d'af al gav d'lo ata acher ve'afsakei lekola. Nope.
The same law would be even if there was not a marriage
in between and the rumor was not interrupted. You're right. The scenario
has to be without witnesses, but she would not have to divorce
ראובן Reuven either way. So אי איכא עדים מפקינן, Ei ika edin
mafkinan, if there are witnesses, that's the only case we'll force a
divorce. אי ליכא עדים לא מפקינן, Ei leka edin lo mafkinan, without
witnesses we won't. So then why did it speak about another guy
marrying her in between if we don't force a divorce regardless? So
the גמרא Gemara says, והכי קאמר, Vehachi ka'amar, this is what it's
saying: דאף על גב דאתא אחר ואפסקה, D'af al gav d'ata acher
ve'afsakei, even though she married another guy in between, ואפסקה לקלא ve'afsakei
lekala and interrupted the rumors, לכתחילה לא יכנוס, L'chatchila lo yichnos, לכתחילה
l'chatchila she shouldn't marry ראובן. Reuven. So the חידוש chiddush is not
that she doesn't have to divorce ראובן. Reuven. She wouldn't have to
divorce ראובן Reuven even if she married him immediately. If there were
no witnesses, you're not going to force a divorce. רב Rav is
really taking a very like מיקל meikel approach here. No witnesses, you're
not going to force a divorce. The only point of the ברייתא
braita that said if the guy interrupted was to be מחמיר, machmir,
then even if a guy interrupted, לכתחילה l'chatchila she shouldn't marry ראובן
Reuven after the second divorce.
Okay. מיתיבי. Meitvei. I'll ask you on this. במה דברים אמורים, Bamei
devarim amurim, we have a ברייתא braita that says, when is this
true that you don't force a divorce from ראובן? Reuven? כשאין לה
בנים, Keshein lah banim, when she didn't have children with her first
husband. אבל יש לה בנים, Aval yesh lah banim, if she had
children with her first husband, לא תצא, Lo tetzei, she should not
get divorced, right? Because if there are children from the first husband,
if you force a divorce from ראובן, Reuven, that is the best
way to reinforce the rumor by forcing her to get divorced from
the second guy. Why would בית דין beis din go to the
extent of forcing her to get divorced from the second guy unless
it was true that she was having an affair with him? So
you don't want to have to reinforce the rumor. You're concerned that
they're now עובר over because they're sleeping together and you're not allowed
to continue to sleep together if you had an affair, you know,
if there was an adulterous affair. Fine. But the tradeoff is that
you're making everybody believe that the rumor was true. That's why you're
forcing the divorce. And that's not a price worth paying if there
are kids that are going to get hurt in the mix. If
there are kids that are now going to be perceived to be
ממזרים. mamzeirim. So if she had... right, because if they were having
an affair, then who's the real father of these kids? Right? You
don't know who the real father of these kids is, you start
suspecting their parentage. Okay, so you will not force a divorce from
ראובן Reuven if there are kids she had with her first husband.
וכשאין לה בנים U'keshein lah banim means you do force it...
you do force it when there's no kids.
Ah, so במה דברים אמורים Bamei devarim amurim is when do we
force the divorce,
which is what the משנה Mishna says. Right. But when there are
children, we don't because it'll just reinforce... because forcing a divorce reinforces
the rumor and we don't want the kids to pay the price.
But ואם באו עדי טומאה, Ve'im bo'u edei tumah, if there are
witnesses that they were having an affair, אפילו יש לה כמה בנים
תצא. Afilu yesh lah kama banim tetzei. So we don't care. So
then we can't allow her to stay married to ראובן. Reuven. We
know they were having an affair. We know that they're אסור assur
to one another because a woman who commits, you know, who commits
adultery is forbidden to the man she was having the affair with.
We can't tolerate that. We have objective proof she was having an
affair. We force a divorce and it's too, you know, okay, the
kids... they're not necessarily ממזרים, mamzeirim, maybe there will be some suspicions
raised, but nevertheless we feel that we're not able to tolerate this
union even if there are kids in the mix. So what does
that show you? It shows you that the basic הלכה halacha was
said without witnesses. Here's with witnesses, you force a divorce even if
there are kids. Okay. Without witnesses, then we said it depends: if
there's no kids, force a divorce; if there are kids, don't force
a divorce. So it shows you that even without witnesses, we will
force a divorce as long as there's no kids. Right? And רב
Rav says you don't force a divorce unless there are witnesses. Here
the ברייתא braita is very clear. If there are no kids, you
force the divorce even in the absence of witnesses. Yes, David?
What's the witnesses actually observe?
Well, we'll get to that. Did they actually... I mean, but they
basically observed them having sex. Like how explicitly did they see them?
I mean, you know, did they see them under the sheet? There's
a discussion in a different גמרא Gemara about the basic... I mean
the basic two possibilities is: one is עד שיראו כדרך המנאפים. Ad
she'yiru k'derech ham'nafim. They saw them acting like people engaged in sex.
Okay. So they sort of didn't actually see the genitals. Okay. But
they saw everything that made it very clear that they were actually...
it wasn't just they were outside a locked room and they heard
noises. They actually directly saw, but you know, they saw the bodies
coming together, whatever, without actually seeing the genitals. And the other הלכה,
halacha, again, different questions for whether it is to assume an affair
and therefore to assume she has to get divorced from her husband
and can't marry. Or then the question of, let's say, to actually
Michael's question about if you're actually going to try to execute somebody,
you might need even more like direct evidence. The other phrase is,
the other possibility is כמכחול
בשפופרת. K'michol b'shfoferet. See it like the applicator in the eyelash tube.
Okay. So you can figure out that metaphor. Yes.
So you're saying force the divorce... she could be getting divorced against
her will.
Well yes, that's the question about בית דין Beis Din when it's,
so when it says יוציא yotzi it means we force it.
Force it even if she...
Sure. That's the whole חידוש chiddush about this. Okay. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this. So anyway, it's clear that when there are
no kids, we're talking without witnesses, and where no kids we still
force a divorce. It's a proof against רב. Rav. So the גמרא
Gemara says alright, you're right. Fine. רב מוקי לה למתניתין. Rav muki
lah lemasnisin. So רב Rav would say the משנה Mishnah is talking
about דיש לה בנים ויש לה עדים. deish lah banim ve-ish lah
edim. Fine. When רב Rav said the משנה Mishnah is that there
are witnesses, he was assuming a case that there are kids, and
because there are kids, he had to say that there were witnesses.
Because if without witnesses we wouldn't have done it since there are
kids. But basically רב Rav doesn't disagree. No kids רב Rav would
agree you don't need witnesses. So the גמרא Gemara says, so why
is רב Rav making things complicated? So the גמרא Gemara says, ומאי
דוחקיה דרב לאוקמי למתניתין ביש לה בנים ויש לה עדים? u-mai duchkeih
de-Rav le-ukmeih le-masnisin be-ish lah banim ve-ish lah edim?
What forced רב Rav to assume the משנה Mishnah was talking about
kids and then he had to say, oh then the only time
we're going to do it is when there are witnesses? וטעמא דאיכא
עדים מפקינן לה וליכא עדים לא מפקינן? ve-tama de-ika edim mafkinan lah
ve-leka edim lo mafkinan? Because there are witnesses we cause the divorce
and if not, not. לוקמה בשאין לה בנים? lukmah be-she-ein lah banim?
Why not assume the משנה Mishnah is without kids? ואף על גב
דליכא עדים? ve-af al gav de-leka edim? And without kids then there
are no witnesses. Simple read of the משנה, Mishnah, there's a rumor,
no kids, then you force a divorce. אמר רבא מתניתין קשיא ליה.
Amar Rava: masnisin kashya leih. No,
the משנה Mishnah bothered him. מאי אירייא דתני הוציאוה? mai irya de-tani
hotziuha?
Why does it say that they forced, literally it means they took
her away from her first husband? ליתני הוציאה? lisni hotziah?
Why doesn't it just say her first husband divorced her after the
rumors? אלא, ella,
so what would be the only case בית דין Beis Din would
have forced her to divorce her first husband? כהוציאוה דבי דין. ke-hotziuha
de-bei din.
Taking her away means the court forced the first divorce, the first
divorce from her first husband. ובי דין בעדים הוא דמפקי. u-vei din
be-edim hu de-mapki. And therefore the only time בית דין Beis Din
would have forced a divorce from her first husband is with witnesses.
So basically רב Rav is not being מחדש mechadesh anything according to
הלכה, halacha, everybody agrees. No witnesses, you force a divorce if there
are no kids. With witnesses, you force a divorce even if there
are kids. Nobody debates the fact. רב Rav is just saying I'm
bothered by the language of the משנה Mishnah that it sounds like
they forced her to divorce her first husband. Who is forcing a
divorce from the first husband? So it must be the scenario is
that there are witnesses and there are kids, and therefore that's why
they forced her to divorce. But I'm not debating the הלכה. halacha.
הלכה halacha would be true either way. Okay, if there's no witnesses,
then it's when the husband chooses to divorce her. If there are
witnesses, we'll force a divorce. But either way, even without witnesses we
will force her to divorce the second guy who goes ahead and
gets married. So that basically removes any הלכתא חידוש hilchasa chiddush of
רב. Rav. But now what the גמרא Gemara is going to say,
and this is very important להלכה, le-halacha, is it's going to say
no, actually רב Rav is very serious. We will never force a
divorce ever from the second guy without witnesses. Okay, let's go look
at the next
line. Let's take a look. So yeah, despite the rumors, without witnesses
we will never force a divorce. Exactly. So the גמרא Gemara says,
well, forcing a divorce reinforces the rumor. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this: ואיבעית אימא האי מתניתין הני ברייתות ve-iba'is eima hai masnisin
hanei baraisos that we quoted that make it clear that you would
force a divorce without witnesses, right? If there are no kids, you
force a divorce without witnesses. That's very clear from the ברייתא. baraisa.
So that ברייתא baraisa is רבי היא. Rebbi hi. That's the position
of רבי, Rebbi, but רב Rav disagrees. You know, either he claims
that the משנה Mishnah assumes otherwise or רב Rav is a תנא
tanna and רב Rav is allowed to disagree. So you're right, there's
a ברייתא baraisa that says that without witnesses you would divorce as
long as there's no kids. But that's רבי. Rebbi. That's not רב.
Rav. Now how do we know that this is a unique position
of רבי? Rebbi? דתניא, detanya, we taught in a ברייתא: baraisa:
רוכל יוצא, rochel yotzei, the spice seller, we would say the merchant,
we would say the traveling salesman, so guy, husband comes home from
work and as he's coming home from work the traveling salesman is
leaving the house.
We would say the milkman. The milkman's leaving the house, ואישה חוגרת
בסינר, ve-ishah chogeret be-sinar, and his wife is putting on her girdle.
Okay, so that's pretty... wonder what just happened here. Okay, so but
there's no direct evidence, and who knows, always possible some other explanation.
אמר רבי הואיל ומכוער הדבר תצא. Amar Rebbi: ho'il u-mechuar ha-davar tetzei.
Because the thing is disgusting, unseemly, they have to get divorced. Now
it's an interesting phrase מכוער הדבר. mechuar ha-davar. Does that mean that
we definitely need to assume it happened, or means like even if
we can't assume it happened, it's suspicious enough that we don't want
to continue the marriage in this state of this type of suspicious
event having occurred? Right? The phrase מכוער הדבר. mechuar ha-davar. You could
have used a different phrase. You could say הואיל ויש רגליים לדבר
תצא, ho'il ve-yesh raglayim la-davar tetzei, right? That's a different phrase. Since
there's good evidence, since there's good basis for assuming something happened, they
have to get divorced. מכוער הדבר mechuar ha-davar might be saying I
don't know if it happened or not, but it's so unseemly that
to continue the marriage after this type of suspicion
happened with this type of thing that occurred that gives whether it
happened or not it's improper to
continue. concerns. Okay. רוק למעלה מן הכילה, rok l'ma'la min hakila, let's
say there is spit on the canopy above the bed. So I
don't exactly get spit might be a euphemism meaning semen although Rashi
doesn't think so. Anyway, אמר רבי הולך אחר מכוער דבר תצא, Amar
Rebbe holech achar mechuar davar tetzei, they say it's a euphemism there.
Rashi thinks it's literal.
Okay. אמר רבי הולך אחר מכוער דבר תצא, Amar Rebbe holech achar
mechuar davar tetzei, you know, all right, there's something pretty suspicious going
on here, it's not seemly, she has to get divorced. מנעלים הפוכים
תחת המיטה, min'alim hapuchim tachat hamita,
the shoes are upturned under the bed, what exactly that's supposed to
mean. אמר רבי הולך אחר מכוער דבר תצא. Amar Rebbe holech achar
mechuar davar tetzei. So מנעלים הפוכים לחזי דמאן נינהו? min'alim hapuchim lachzei
d'man ninhu? So the Gemara assumes that the shoes are overturned meaning
maybe they're the רוכל, rochel, you know, the spice seller's shoes. So
why don't you just look at them? And they're turned over so
you can't see whose shoes they are. So just look, look at
whose shoes they are. So the Gemara says אלא מקום מנעלים הפוכים,
ela m'kom min'alim hapuchim, the place of the shoes is reversed. Again,
not exactly clear what that means. Rashi either says that there's either
evidence that somebody put their shoes under the bed and left some
mark there and turned them upside down, there aren't shoes there any
now but it looks like somebody's put their shoes under the bed.
Or that the shoes are in the wrong
place, like where her shoes normally are is where his shoes are,
like something's been happening with the,
you know, in the bedroom, that things aren't the way they should
be. What?
It's getting like less and less.
Oh, that's also true, possibly it's less and less, right. Yeah, yeah,
yeah, that's true. Yeah, yeah, yeah, that's a good point. Okay. So
anyway, what do you see? So Rebbe says even if there's not
straight evidence, even if there's suspicion, תצא. tetzei. So Rav says you
know what, you're right. There's a ברייתא braita that says if they
got married even by a rumor, even without evidence they have to
get divorced as long as there's no kids. That's Rebbe. I don't
think that's correct. I think that the only time you'll force a
divorce is if there's direct, if there's direct evidence. Okay, I disagree
with Rebbe. And that is a big question because nowadays you know
this actually happens, right? You know, cases of adultery and affairs and
suspicion and evidence. And sometimes the hardest thing in הלכה halacha is
that you've got a suspicious husband that actually hires a private investigator.
This actually happened and they actually get pictures. It's the worst. And
then they want to reconcile. Wonderful, you know, you had to go
ahead and get pictures, right? So the less direct evidence you have,
even if there's a lot of circumstantial evidence, Rav would say if
there's no עדים edim you don't have to get divorced. Okay, only
if there's עדים. edim. Anyway, we're talking about the second guy, presumably
what's true about the second guy is also true about the first
guy. Right, the same type of evidence that you would force a
divorce from her husband she's married to now would presumably be the
same amount of evidence you would need to force a divorce or
you know from the second guy although I'll mention תוספות Tosafot in
a minute about that. But let's just see how the Gemara, what
the first would presumably be the same as the second. Her original
husband and the guy she's suspected of having the affair with. Let's
just see the הלכה. halacha. I'll take the questions in a minute.
The Gemara says והלכתא כוותיה דרב, v'hilchata k'vateih d'Rav,
we rule like Rav that you only force a divorce if there's
witnesses.
והלכתא כוותיה דרבי, v'hilchata k'vateih d'Rebbe, and we rule like Rebbe that
you force a divorce even with circumstantial evidence. So the Gemara says
ah, those aren't saying the same thing. קשיא הלכתא אהלכתא, kashya hilchata
a'hilchata, those contradict.
לא קשיא. lo kashya. הא בקלא דפסיק הא בקלא דלא פסיק. ha
b'kala d'pasik ha b'kala d'lo pasik. When will we force a divorce
without witnesses? It's only if it is a rumor that doesn't stop.
Okay, and that somehow it's quite fascinating how you know it's אסור
asur to tell לשון הרע, lashon hara, but somehow if rumors keep
on,
you know, keep on don't die, we sort of, we take it
like if there's smoke there's fire type of an attitude and we
actually think that that somewhat creates some basis for believing it's true.
So we're now going to talk about what that means that the
rumor doesn't stop.
Do kids make a difference? To this rumor?
Well, kids? Oh, yeah, well, we'll talk about that in a minute.
Yeah, no, with kids everybody agrees you'd need witnesses.
Okay. קלא דלא פסיק. kala d'lo pasik. Well, the Gemara says like
this, so it's קלא דלא פסיק וליכא עדים כרבי. kala d'lo pasik
v'leka edim k'Rebbe. If it's a rumor that doesn't cease then we
would force a divorce like Rebbe. Again, without kids. קלא דפסיק, kala
d'pasik, if it's a rumor that ceases, then the only time we
would force a divorce is ואיכא עדים כרב, v'ika edim k'Rav, only
if there are witnesses. So basically will we force a divorce based
on without direct evidence, without witnesses? Yes, in the case of a
rumor that doesn't cease. And that's the compromise of Rav and Rebbe.
תוספות Tosafot points out Rav and Rebbe themselves wouldn't have agreed to
this compromise. Right? Rav would say even a rumor that doesn't end.
Rebbe might have said even a rumor that, even if the rumor
doesn't continue. So but you know that's the idea of a compromise,
you take a middle position. So the Gemara is going to פסקן
pasken that it will be concerned about it if it's a rumor
that doesn't cease. Now what does that mean? So the Gemara says
וקלא דלא פסיק עד כמה? v'kala d'lo pasik ad kama? What does
that mean? How long does the rumor have to go for? So
אמר אביי אמרה לי אם, Amar Abaye amra li em, my mother
said to me, which wasn't his mother, it was his... nursemaid, Abbaye
was orphaned and his nursemaid brought him up and he called her
his mother. So דומי דמאסא, dumi d'masa, question what דומי dumi means.
רש"י Rashi says it either means like the, it either means like
the
gossips in the city, or it means like people are saying בדדומי,
bid'dumi, people are saying out of you know, they're they're guessing,
they're suspicious or they're speculating but they don't know for sure. Anyway
but the people that are rumoring are saying it, are saying it
יומא ופלגא yoma upalga for a day and a half. My God,
that is not too long for people to be rumoring about something
and for that to constitute a קלא דלא פסיק. kala d'lo pasik.
So that's a pretty low standard, which is a pretty מחמיר machmir
position. ולא אמרינן, V'lo amrinan, now the גמרא Gemara tries to pull
back a little bit, אלא דלא פסיק ביני וביני. ela d'lo pasik
beini uveini. That's only if it did not you know, if they've
been talking about it for a day and a half without stop.
אבל פסיק ביני וביני, Aval pasik beini uveini, if there's a period
they stopped, sort of the gossip stopped talking about it, הפסיק, hifsik,
it stopped. Now I don't exactly know who's measuring this, what does
it mean? People are talking every single every single second? How much
of an interruption in a day and a half? What, if I
talked about it for an hour and then I waited three hours,
that's an interruption? I don't, how many people? I don't understand this.
Okay, I don't understand how you translate this into practice. ולא אמרינן
V'lo amrinan okay, דלא פסיק מחמת יראה. d'lo pasik machmat yira. But
if they interrupt during that day and a half and it's sort
of and then it's not considered a continuous rumor, that would only
be a legitimate interruption if it wasn't because they were afraid. Like
they like they saw, they thought that like the people they were
rumoring about was, were going to go ahead and do something and
there'd be some recrimination. אבל פסיק מחמת יראה, Aval pasik machmat yira,
if they were, there was a reason that they would have been
gossiping about it were they not afraid that they would have, there
would be some consequence, then מחמת יראה הוא, machmat yira hu, okay
then the interruption isn't meaningful. Again, it's so funny that we are
giving all this הלכתי halachic weight to gossip. ולא אמרינן אלא דליכא
אויבים. V'lo amrinan ela d'leika oyvim. Now this is probably the best
way to get out of this, which is, all of the idea
that a rumor creates a basis for divorce is only if the
people don't have any any enemies. Okay, 'cause then we could say,
אבל איכא אויבים, aval ika oyvim, if the, you know, if the
man or the woman have enemies, אויבים הוא דאפקי ליה לקלא. oyvim
hu d'apki lei l'kala. So the enemies are the ones that are
invested in spreading the rumor and then you can discount it. Okay?
So hopefully maybe there are some real צדיקים tzaddikim out there that
have no enemies in the world, and and for them it would
be a problem. But anyway, that certainly would be a way that
a lot of people could sort of say, you know, of course
what happens if it's not the enemies that are doing the rumoring?
It's the friends that are, sometimes your friends are your worst enemies.
So anyway, okay. So, okay,
fine.
So that's what we have, that's presumably is the הלכה. halacha. So
presumably the הלכה halacha is, is that even on the basis of
rumors, again, if there are kids then you're and then you're only
going to force the divorce from the second guy if there's direct
evidence. But it sounds like the conclusion here is, although we've seen
some possible outs, but strong rumors and certainly maybe some strong evidence
even if it's not direct testimony would be enough to force a
divorce. Is that really how it plays out למעשה? l'maaseh? So there
is a, a a
תוספות Tosafot that makes a slight little point which is which is
huge. Take a look at the תוספות, Tosafot, אמר רב הרי חול
המועד דבר Amar Rav harei chol hamoed davar back on כ"ד עמוד
ב'. chaf dalet amud bet. He says, אומר רבינו תם,
Omer Rabbeinu
Tam, כדתיצי מן הרוכל אם תנשא. kedetitzi min harochel im tinasei. When
does רבי Rebbi say that if there's like these suspicious things she
has to get divorced? That means it's enough to make her divorce
from the guy she's suspected of having an affair with, if she
wound up marrying the milkman. Then we would force a divorce based
on this evidence or based on this suspicion.
דכולה סוגיא איירי בנטען. D'chula sugya ayri b'nitan. It's all about do
we force a divorce from the guy who was suspected of having
the affair, not about the husband. It's about her staying married to
the guy she was suspected of having an affair with. דאין לומר
תצא מן הבעל. De'ein lomar tetzei min habaal. We're not talking about
getting divorced from the husband that any of this would suffice. דאין
אשה נאסרת אבעלה אלא על ידי קינוי וסתירה. De'ein isha ne'eseret a'baalah
ela al yedei kinui v'stira. The only way a woman would be
forced to divorce her husband would be like it says in מסכת
סוטה, Masechet Sotah, there's עדים edim that her husband warned her, then
there's עדים edim that she was in private with the man. Like
it went through the סוטה Sotah process, which is very specific.
או שיראו כדרך המנאפים, O sheyiru k'derech haminafim, or they actually saw
them, they might not have had to see like the genitals but
they actually saw them having sex. Okay, so that's the only time
we would divorce a woman from her husband. So תוספות Tosafot basically
takes the גמרא Gemara that very reasonably could have been read that
as long as there's some type of reasonable suspicion and certainly if
people are gossiping about it and some type of evidence, you have
to force a woman to divorce her husband. תוספות Tosafot says no,
we're just talking about if she marries the second guy. From the
husband, she's already married to him, we'll never force a divorce unless
there's direct evidence that they were actually having sex.
And the kids are from the
first husband or the second husband? No, the kids' case is when
it's about the second guy and that's from the first husband. But
תוספות Tosafot is making the point that we would never, although the
גמרא Gemara seems, רבי'ס Rebbi's case seemed to introduce the same type
of standard ויז א וי vis-à-vis the husband, תוספות is insisting no,
we're just talking about the standard to apply to the man she's
suspected of having an affair with if she goes ahead and marries
him, but to the husband... To actually force a divorce from her
husband, that would only be if there's ממש *mamash* direct witness, direct
evidence of seeing them have sex, not just
circumstantial. One could even say, look, I know cases that happen like
this. Okay, you know that she met up with this guy in
a motel room. Okay? Alright? You didn't see them having sex? Maybe
they were going having a meeting. Maybe they changed their minds in
the end. Who knows what? Okay, so that takes a גמרא Gemara.
*Gemara* that would have created a
real, challenging halachic demand that would have been very, very hard
to apply in real life and would lead to a lot of
divorces and just saying no, that's all just about if she goes
ahead and marries the other guy. Okay, but in terms of her
remaining with her husband, that you need really direct evidence. Yes?
I think there's a fundamental piece that I'm missing here.
There's no עדים *eidin*, there's no evidence, so we do not force
her to divorce the milkman, right?
No, no, no, no, no. No, if there's no—if there's rumor or
if there's some type of suspicious thing, we do force her to
divorce the milkman. No, but there's no—there's nothing. There's a rumor but
it stopped and whatever.
Right, so we do not force the divorce from the milkman. Right.
Where's husband number one?
Husband number one divorced her because he didn't like the rumors. And
then she went and married the milkman.
You have to assume that somewhere along the way, husband number one
divorced her.
Right.
But the question is—but she didn't want that divorce?
Doesn't matter, it was before רבינו גרשום *Rabbeinu Gershom*.
Doesn't matter if she wanted the divorce. Okay, fine, that was the
little piece. Right, right. Okay, yes.
I just wanted to make also sure, so even though there were
kids from the second—let's say there were no kids from the first
husband, and there were kids from the second husband and there are
all these rumors and forcing the divorce may lead to more rumors
and these kids—oh, forcing the divorce, they must be that these kids
are ממזרים *mamzeirim*.
No, they wouldn't be ממזרים *mamzeirim*. I'm sorry? They wouldn't be ממזרים
*mamzeirim*. Kids that are born as a result of a man and
a woman who had an affair living together, they're over on a
לאו *lav*, the kids that result are not ממזרים *mamzeirim*.
No, but the rumors were, oh, she had sex while she was
married with the first guy. So what? Doesn't make the kids—she marries
the milkman, had kids with him.
Yeah. Doesn't mean that the kids she has with the milkman are
ממזרים *mamzeirim*. It's only ממזר *mamzeir* that could be suspected about the
first husband. Okay, yes.
רבינו גרשום *Rabbeinu Gershom* was the one who
said you can only have one
wife and that you can't divorce your wife against her will. Yeah,
that's what I was wondering about.
He said that in the year one thousand. Okay, so now the
משנה Mishna *Mishna* says like this. All right, so anyway, huge תוספות
*Tosafos*. All right, so תנן התם *tenan hatam*, back to the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara*. We taught over there. המוציא את אשתו *hamotzi et ishto*,
you see, this is why you work through all of the two
brothers marrying two sisters and all of that so you could get
to today's דף *daf*. Okay, so תנן *tenan*. תנן התם המוציא את
אשתו משום שם רע *tenan hatam hamotzi et ishto mishum shem ra*,
if a man divorces his wife, chooses to divorce his wife because
there are suspicions of her having an affair, that's what שם רע
*shem ra* means, לא יחזיר *lo yachazir*. He cannot choose to remarry
her after. Why? Not because—not because of rumors, as we're going to
see because of the next case. Let's read the next case. משום
נדר neder *mishum neder*, let's say he divorced her because she made
a vow that he felt was intolerable and he wasn't able to
live with and he
wasn't מיפר *meifer* it, it was too late. So, and he couldn't
live with her with this vow. לא יחזיר *lo yachazir*, he cannot
remarry her. So obviously, it's not about rumors here. So what's it
about? With this issue of the vow, what it's about is, is
about—he'll divorce his wife because of the vow or because there's a
suspicion she had an affair. She'll go and marry another man. And
then he'll say—and then the woman will have gone to some sage
and got the vow annulled. You know, and find—because there's ways you
can annul vows. You find a פתח *petach* and whatever, we'll learn
in מסכת נדרים *Maseches Nedarim*. Or some evidence will come to bear
and the husband will say, oh, I realize you were telling the
truth, you weren't having an affair with that guy. You know what?
Had I known that you really weren't having an affair, I never
would have divorced you. Had I known that the vow could have
been annulled, I never would have divorced you. So the fact that
now you're married to another guy and have kids, those are all
kids of ממזרים *mamzeirim*, the marriage isn't good, the divorce was always
בטל *batel*, right? So that's where he's afraid he's going to say.
If these are the things, we're afraid he's going to say, well,
I only divorced assuming these things were true. Now that I find
out that they're not, the whole divorce is בטל *batel*. And we
don't want her to always and her kids to always be in
danger of their status being changed because he's going to claim, oh,
I never meant it if had I realized I wouldn't have. So
what we say to him is, make sure you're divorcing
her—there's going to be no opportunity for remarriage. Halachically, we're not going
to let you remarry her. So if you're divorcing her, you cannot
claim it's just because I thought the נדר neder. *neder*, it's just
because I thought this, it has to be a deeper, more profound
reason because there's no opportunity for go-backs here. And therefore, if you
know that there's no opportunity to remarry and still the man goes
ahead and divorces, then he has no basis of saying I only
did it because I thought of the rumors, I only did it
because of the נדר neder *neder*. If that was the only reason,
you would not have done it knowing that there was no opportunity
to remarry.
Unless
she—only
if she marries someone else? Let's say she doesn't marry someone.
Oh, doesn't—even
if she doesn't marry someone. Even a minute, a day later, he
can't remarry her. So if you can always remarry, you can say,
I only did it because I thought whatever and I figured even
if I'm wrong, we can always— always get remarried. Okay, but if
you know that you can never get remarried, then obviously we have
to say that the דעת is much deeper and you can't claim
you wouldn't have done it had this not been the case.
What's actually, what's an example of a נדר neder, that he would
have taken? What would he have...
No, she took a נדר.
Oh, what'd she say?
I don't know. She took a נדר that like she's not going
to,
all the housework is אסור assur on her.
You know? So, he... I can't live with a wife who's not
going to do the housework, something like that. I don't know. So,
okay.
I'm sorry, that was a little sexist. But okay, it's within the
context of the גמרא. Gemara Yes. Alright, yes. And that's how we
hold, because
that he
can't remarry her in those cases?
If she has not been involved with
anybody else, can he remarry her? Not if the divorce... I mean,
that's the הלכה. halacha. How it plays out in practice, I don't
know the תשובה teshuva literature, but the הלכה halacha is that rabbinically
we don't let her remarry. Right. Okay, so it says like this.
So, it says... It might be different today also with רבנו גרשום,
Rabbeinu Gershom, the fact that she needs to agree to it. So
that might somewhat change some of those dynamics. Once it's no longer
unilateral, his ability to claim had I known, I would, you know,
if, you know, I wouldn't have done it and so on. Although
it still technically is unilateral, but there is חרם רבנו גרשום. cherem
Rabbeinu Gershom. Anyway...
No, not at all.
Meaning like a minute later he can't marry her. Right. She wouldn't
have gone off and married somebody else.
Doesn't matter about marrying somebody else. We're afraid that... Oh, yes, that,
yes, fine. Okay, so. Okay. מאי חזר? Mai chazar? שלחו ליה רבה
בר הונא לרבה בר רב נחמן. Shalchu leh Rabba bar Huna l'Rabba
bar Rav Nachman. ילמדנו רבינו: Yelamdenu Rabbeinu: היכא דכנס מאי מוציא? Heicha
d'kannas mai motzi?
In this case, בדיעבד, b'diavad, if he went ahead and did remarry
her, when he divorced her because of rumors or divorced her because
of a נדר, do we let them stay remarried? Because that's our
theme, right? The whole reason we got into all these discussions was
because the משנה Mishna said by the case of the ספק, safek,
if you're married to רחל Rachel and לאה, Leah, both brothers shouldn't
marry, and if they married, they can stay married. And then we
said if there's a rumor about an affair with a non-Jewish woman,
don't get married, if you're married, you can stay married. If there's
a rumor with a married woman, don't get married, and if you
get married, then you have to get divorced. So the theme is
כנס, kannas, if the marriage took place, is it יוציא yotzi or
not יוציא? yotzi? So he's asking that question in this case. We
say you're not supposed to remarry, a man's not supposed to remarry
his wife if he divorces her for these reasons. If he did
remarry her, what's the story? Does he have to divorce her? אמר
ליה תנינא, Amar lei tanina,
we taught: הנטען על אשת איש ויוציאוה מתחת ידו אף על פי
שכנס יוציא. Ha-nitan al eshet ish ve-yotzi'ua mi-tachat yado af al pi
she-kannas yotzi. We taught when the man married the woman who he
was suspected of having an adulterous affair with, he בדיעבד b'diavad has
to divorce her. So he thinks that's the standard rule. בדיעבד, B'diavad,
if you're not allowed to marry, then you gotta get divorced בדיעבד.
b'diavad. אמר ליה מי דמי? Amar lei mi dami? How can you
compare them? התם הוציאוה. Hatam hotzi'ua. There, it says they forced her
to divorce her husband, which at least according to רבי, Rebbi, רב
Rav meant there were witnesses that saw that she committed adultery. So
that's why we won't let her stay married to the second guy.
הכא הוציאה. Hacha hotzi'ah.
Here, he divorced her on his own. So basically the basic point
being that the reason, right? The only case of all these scenarios
where we've seen so far you force a divorce is the case
of adultery, of suspected adultery. So he says you can't make a
rule from the suspected adultery case. Certainly according to רבי, Rebbi, he
says it wasn't even suspected adultery, that there were witnesses. So you
can't make a rule from that. ורבה בר רב נחמן מתניתין נמי
הוציאה תנן. Ve-Rabba bar Rav Nachman matnitin nami hotzi'ah tenan.
But רבה בר רב נחמן Rabba bar Rav Nachman thinks the משנה
Mishna is not that there were witnesses. It means that the husband
willingly divorced her. And so he wants to use the case of
the adultery, of the suspected adultery as a basis to say you
always have to divorce if you weren't allowed to get married. ואכתי
מי דמי? Ve-achti mi dami? But still it's not similar. Even if
it was only... even if there weren't witnesses. הכא בעל והתם בועל.
Hacha ba'al ve-hatam bo'el.
There, it's much more problematic. It's the guy we think committed adultery
with her. We're not going to be so tolerant of the fact
that they are now married and living together, even if it's only
a rumor. They were, you know, that's a really deeply problematic thing
that they... that's a really אסור assur thing that they did.
So the marriage now is something that's deeply problematic. As opposed to
here, it's the legitimate husband. He divorced her, he remarried her. There's
nothing ugly or wrong that happened. They just went against the rabbinic
stricture of remarrying, but there's nothing deeply problematic. So here we should
tolerate it if they get remarried. Okay? So the גמרא Gemara says:
אמר ליה שפיר דמי. Amar lei shapir dami. No,
I think it is comparable. אהדדי. Ah-dadi. They are comparable. הכא אמרו
רבנן לא יכנוס ואם כנס יוציא. Hacha amru rabanan lo yichnos ve-im
kannas yotzi. At the end of the day, I don't worry about
sociological issues, I don't worry about anything, I'm just a technical הלכה.
halacha.
You say don't get married, and if you get married, divorce. הכא
נמי אמרו רבנן לא יחזיר ואם כנס יוציא. Hacha nami amru rabanan
lo yachzir ve-im kannas yotzi. Don't remarry, and if you went against
it, you have to get divorced. Of course, the problem is that
most of the cases in the משנה were cases where בדיעבד b'diavad
you don't have to get divorced. There's only one case, the adultery
case, which is the... which is a בדיעבד. b'diavad. Anyway, the גמרא
says: ולא היא. Ve-lo hee. It says the גמרא rejects it. התם
אלומי אלמי לקליה. Hatam alumi almi l'kaley. There when the... suspected adulterer
marries this woman, he's reinforcing the rumor. Right? Ah, we see, must
be true, you know, they went and they got married afterwards. So
again, that makes it intolerable. Of course, us then forcing them to
get divorced also reinforces the rumor, but anyway, but the act of
them getting married was more intolerable. הכא אמרינן קמי בקלא ולא סה,
hacha amreinan kammai bekala velo sa, here, if he divorces her because
there was a rumor and then he remarried her, it serves the
opposite purpose. It shows that the rumor must have been false. Why
else would he have remarried her? So there's other things to factor
in than just the technical question of were you over on the
דרבנן derabbanan or not. Again, what's also fascinating is again that five
out of the, four out of the five cases in the משניות
mishnayot just now were all that בדיעבד bedieved it's okay. There was
only one case that בדיעבד bedieved it was not okay. Okay, okay,
I guess we will end here.